原视频名：SpaceX's Biggest Starship Flight Is A Spectacular Success Even After Crash Landing
原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/egHxiX40eJY
原视频发布日期：20201209
字幕翻译/压制：旋火
Hello it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是Scott Manley
And it has been an epic and exciting day for fans of rockets and space travel
对于火箭和太空旅行的爱好者来说 今天是史诗般的激动人心的一天
because this vehicle finally got to fly to 12.5 kilometers in spectacular style.
因为这枚航天器终于以壮观的姿态飞到了12.5公里处
Now this would be the first test of a highly risky and experimental maneuver
那么 这会是这个高风险的实验性机动的第一次测试
which required everything to go right.
这要求一切都要正确实施
So I had to make sure that the dressing, gown of doom was safely stashed out of the way
所以 我必须确保那件末日礼服安全地被藏在了一边
so that it could not influence results.
以至于无法影响结果
So this was serial number eight.
所以这艘飞船是序列号八
It had three Raptor engines including serial number 42
它有三台猛禽发动机 包括序列号42
and initially they all lit together
而最初这些发动机都是一起点火的
and the massive 160 foot tall launch vehicle headed towards the sky.
而48.7米高的巨大运载火箭就向天空飞去
This is a monster.
这是一个怪物
This is like a 12 story building flying.
这就像一栋12层楼房在飞行
This was the first Starship prototype to fly with a nose cone and flaps.
这是第一架带鼻锥和翼面飞行的Starship原型机
Previously they had built one but it had been destroyed on a launch pad before even flying.
此前曾制造过一个同样带有鼻锥和翼面的(Mk1) 但还没飞起来就在发射台上被毁了
So yeah initially it was trying to climb on three engines.
所以最初它是想靠三台发动机来爬升的
They needed the thrust of all of them.
(因为起飞时)需要所有发动机的推力
This was not a fully fueled spacecraft because that would make it too heavy.
这不是一个完全加满燃料的航天器 因为那会使它太重
You can tell how much propellant is in it by the amount of frosting on the exterior tanks.
你可以通过外部储罐上的结霜量来判断里面有多少推进剂
And amateur tank watchers actually got a lot of time to examine
而实际上 业余的储罐观察者们有很多时间来检查这件事
just how much frost was being put on the side of the tanks
也就是储罐的侧面结了多少霜
because initially they were going to fly on tuesday.
因为最初他们打算在周二飞行
They filled up the rocket.
他们把火箭加注好了
It was on the pad.
火箭放置在了发射台上
They counted down and began spinning up the engines.
他们倒计时 并开始转动发动机(的涡轮泵)
And at 1.3 seconds the engines stopped the ignition process.
在倒计时1.3秒时 发动机停止了点火过程
Apparently there was a problem with the actual ignition inside the engine.
显然是发动机内部的点火装置出了问题
So they decided not to launch and that was an entirely an automated process.
所以他们决定不发射 而这完全是一个自动化的过程
On wednesday they got started a little bit earlier
周三 他们早一点启动了发动机
but then two minutes before launch they called a hold.
但在发射前两分钟 他们在呼号中暂停了发射他们说停停
And it took them an hour and a half to ultimately recycle the vehicle.
而之后 他们花了一个半小时才让航天器恢复发射状态
And this was the third attempt and it flew obviously.
而在这第三次尝试中 显然它飞了起来
Now we didn't actually know how it was going to perform its flight.
那么我们并不知道它将如何进行飞行
Now we did know that the mission plan was to carry the vehicle up to 12.5 kilometers
那么我们知道任务计划是将航天器带到12.5公里的高空
and then have it belly flop back down at terminal velocity before performing the landing.
然后让它做机腹翻转机动 以终端速度返回下降 再进行着陆
But we didn't actually know how it would fly to 12.5 kilometers
但我们其实并不知道它是如何飞到12.5公里的
and turned out that lots of people got it wrong.
结果发现很多人都搞错了
That little fireball there is because they just shut down one of the engines
那个小火球是因为他们刚刚关闭了一台发动机
and a lot of amateur observers when they saw that thought that was a failure.
很多爱好者看到后都认为那是个失败
You can see some fire inside there.
你可以看到里面着了一点火
That's trapped gases from the engine that's just shut down.
那是刚刚关闭的发动机所产生的滞留气体
And it's totally normal.
这是完全正常的
But we didn't know that at the time.
但我们当时并不知道这一点
I mean there was a lot of concerned comments about this going wrong.
我是指 有很多对此担心的意见 实际上是错的
But ultimately it's clear.
但最终很清楚
The plan is that they had reached a certain speed
计划是他们已经达到了一定的速度
so they were shutting down the engine
所以他们要关闭发动机
so they could cruise upwards towards their altitude while maintaining control
这样他们就可以在保持控制(速度)的情况下朝着目标高度向上飞行了
because the fins don't actually provide that much control
因为实际上 翼面并没有提供那么多的控制能力
except when they're in the belly flop configuration.
因为翼面是在机腹翻转后的(气动)布局下提供控制的
When they're going straight up like this
而当飞船像这样直起身子的时候
they either have the reaction control thrusters from that cold gas jets
要么通过冷气喷射器驱动的反推力推进器(RCS)
or they have the gimbaling of these rocket thrusters.
要么通过火箭发动机的矢量摆动
So first they shut down one and then they get ready to shut down the next one.
那么他们先关闭了一台发动机 然后准备关闭下一台
And if you look very carefully
如果你仔细观察
that engine that is closest to us in the bottom right.
右下角那个离我们最近的那台发动机
That is engine number 42 the answer to life the universe and how to make grain silos fly.
那就是42号发动机 这是生命的答案 宇宙的答案 以及如何让粮仓飞起来的答案
These are of course the Raptor engines.
这些当然是猛禽发动机
They burn methane and liquid oxygen.
它们燃烧着甲烷和液氧
They generate about 200 tons of thrust.
产生大约200吨的推力
And they use a full flow staged combustion cycle which is super high tech and complicated
使用的是全流量分级燃烧循环 这个超级高科技和复杂的系统
but should result in lower temperatures inside.
但这样的循环会导致其内部的温度较低
So we're about to shut off the second engine.
所以我们就要关闭第二台发动机了
Watch the engine bells in the bottom right.
注意右下角的发动机钟形喷管
As the thrust goes away,
随着推力的消失
they will have to make big gimbal adjustments to keep the vehicle centered, right.
发动机得进行大幅度的矢量摆动 来(让推力的方向)保持在航天器的中心
So they had to shift the entire vehicle over because the center of thrust was now slightly different.
所以他们得将整个航天器平移 因为现在的推力中心略有不同
So this engine is probably running at below full thrust levels
所以这台发动机可能是在低于满推力水平的情况下运行
because what they're now doing is they're coming up towards their apogee.
因为他们现在要做的是向远地点靠近
And it looks more like they're sort of hovering.
看上去更像是在悬停
They're performing the equivalent of a hop.
他们在进行一种类似悬停的机动
But they're doing it at 12 kilometers.
但这可是在12km的高度上
They're translating sideways.
他们在横向平移
Because when they start coming back down
因为当飞船开始往回掉落时
they will actually want to use aerodynamics to control the vehicle and move it around.
他们实际上是想利用空气动力学来控制航天器并使其移动
So they don't want it to be exactly over the launch site
所以他们不希望它正好在发射场的上空
partly because if there's a failure they just like it to smash into somewhere that hasn't got buildings on it.
部分原因是 如果出现失败 他们想把火箭砸到没有建筑物的地方
But secondly they want to actually show that they get a cross-range capabilities.
但其次则是 实际上他们想展示一种横向机动的能力
So yeah that's four minutes that this engine has been running.
那么 是的 这台发动机已经运行四分钟了
That's the longest we've seen a Raptor running.
这是我们见过的最长的猛禽点火时间
Certainly the longest that we've seen one propelling a vehicle in flight.
当然也是推动航天器飞行的猛禽点火的最长时间
So if you look at the condensation and puffs of gas that are coming off the bottom there
那么如果你看一下底部的蒸汽和气体喷出的情况
you can actually see that this is moving sideways rather than moving vertically now.
你就会发现这是在横向移动而不是垂直移动了
Now all of this flight so far has been fed from the main propellant tanks.
那么到目前为止 所有的飞行(动力)都是由主推进剂箱提供的(燃料)
That's the tanks that cover most of the volume of the vehicle.
那就是覆盖了航天器大部分体积的储罐
This engine is about to turn off and it will then have to perform this transition into the belly flop maneuver.
这台发动机即将关闭 然后它就得进行这个过渡到机腹翻转的动作
So it's going to have to flip over and you see actually uses the gimbaling just a little to help it.
那么它必须要翻转 实际上你会发现这是用了一点发动机的矢量推进
And watch the flaps because this has to basically lift these flaps up and down.
那么再看看翼面 因为这基本上是要把这些翼面向上和向下抬起来
I believe they're actuated by electric motors and they have to kind of get it flying horizontally like a skydiver.
我相信它们是由电动机驱动的 而飞船必须得像跳伞运动员一样水平飞行
It wants to present the widest cross-section possible so that it falls at the slowest speed.
飞船得要展示出最宽的横截面 这样才能以最慢的速度下降
This is kind of the signature move of Starship.
这差不多是Starship的招牌动作
Being able to go side-on and control yourself aerodynamically
能够侧着身子 通过空气动力学来控制姿态
means that you can perform re-entry much more quickly
意味着你可以更快地进行再入
because the thing about re-entry heating is the sharper the curve the more heating you have to contend with.
因为在再入加热这个问题上 (外形)曲线越尖锐 你需要应对的热量就越多
So a wide flat body like this gets less heating
那么像这样一个宽大平坦的外表 得到的热量就较少
because it pushes the shock wave the stagnation layer much further out from the body.
因为这样的外形会把激波的停滞层从机身上推离得更远
So at this point it's falling steadily
那么这时它在稳定地下降
and according to Elon this is way more than he expected to actually work.
而根据马一龙的说法 这次试飞实际进行的动作要比他预期的多得多
This was much more successful so that's a good thing.
实际比预期的要更成功 那么这是一件好事
It's beautiful the way this thing is falling.
Starship坠落的方式很美
It kind of got its nose down a little
坠落时 它的机头是稍向下的
because I think they want to traverse, glide just a little.
因为我认为他们想让飞船略微滑行一段距离
It doesn't really glide but it has enough aerodynamic control that it can cross sideways.
这并不是真正的滑行 但通过足够的空气动力学的控制 可以产生横向位移
Now I want you to think about what's going to happen to the propellant in those main tanks.
那么我想让你想想那些主储箱里的推进剂会发生什么
It's all going to fall to the side of the vehicle because the lowest point of the vehicle.
这些推进剂都会落到航天器的侧面 因为那是航天器的最低点
And the propellant is extracted from those tanks
而推进剂会从那些储罐中被提取出来
by pipes or drains in the bottom of those tanks towards the rear.
这是通过储罐底部 通向航天器的尾部的管道来完成的
So those are now exposed to gas.
那么这些管道现在都暴露在气体中
They can't pull fuel from those tanks.
他们不能从这些储罐中抽出燃料
Instead they have a pair of smaller tanks called header tanks.
相反 他们有一对较小的储罐 叫头部储罐
Those are supposed to feed the thrusters for the last moments.
这些储罐是在最后时刻给推进器提供燃料的
And what it's going to do is light up these engines and try to transition back into vertical flight.
而接下来就是点燃这些发动机 并尝试将航天器的姿态转变到垂直飞行
And there we go one two and this is where the thing stops being successful.
那么 一 二……而成功的试飞就在这里戛然而止了
We get green flashes.
我们看到了绿色的闪光
It doesn't slow down.
它没有减速下来
RUD = Rapid Unscheduled Disassembly
And we get a dramatic RUD on the surface.
而我们还看到了一个戏剧性的发生在地面上的快速意外解体(RUD)
But apparently everyone was quite happy with this.
但显然每个人都对此很满意
This was way more successful than they wanted.
这比他们想要的更成功
They demonstrated 95% of their flight profile.
他们验证了95%的飞行时序
The thing that failed right at the end was they were unable to get enough propellant into those engines.
最后失败的原因是他们无法将足够的推进剂注入到发动机中
We also have this angle which is from below and I think this is real time.
我们还有这个从下面看的角度 我觉得这是实时的
So this thing is like a size of a building falling towards you.
那么这像一栋楼大小的飞船向你坠落
It's just insane how slow it looks because of how big it is.
因为它太大了 所以看起来很慢 而这实在太疯狂了
But it's going to light up one engine first and then the second engine.
但它会先点燃一台发动机 然后是第二台发动机
And those will be used to begin to flip over.
而这些发动机将被用来开始翻转
And then you'll see what happens is one of them loses thrust completely
然后你就会看到接下来发生了什么 其中一台发动机完全失去了推力
And then the other turns green bright green.
然后另一台(尾气)变成亮绿色
We've seen green flares from engines before when they start up but this is different.
我们以前见过发动机启动时的绿色火焰 但这次不同
This sequence is only like 10 seconds long so we're slowing things down here.
这个视频片段只有10秒 所以我们把速度放慢了
But look the two rear engines light.
但你看后方的两台发动机点火
These are the ones that shut down earliest.
这两台发动机是最早关闭的发动机
Number 42 does not light during the sequence.
而42号发动机在这个视频片段中并没有点火
It is however seen to gimbal out of the way.
但是可以看到它在向外摆动
So the other two can perform these very wide angle changes to control during the descent.
所以 另外两台发动机就可以在下降过程中进行这些非常大角度的矢量摆动来控制
So yeah you see some flashes of green there.
那么是的 你会看到一些绿色的闪光
Now on Merlin engines you see this green flash as they ignite
现在在梅林发动机点火时 你会看到这种绿色的闪光
because they use a fluid called TEA-TEB, right.
因为他们用的是一种叫TEA-TEB的液体 对吧
Triethylaluminium. Triethylborane.
三乙基铝 三乙基硼烷
And the Borane in that causes a bright green flash.
而其中的硼烷会产生明亮的绿色闪光
It's very good for lighting engines.
这对发动机的点火很有帮助
But Raptors, they use something called torch igniters.
但猛禽发动机用的是一种叫火炬式点火器的东西
And torch igniters work by taking a small amount of fuel and oxidizer
火炬式点火器的工作原理是用少量的燃料和氧化剂
and then using a spark plug.
然后使用火花塞
And they basically create a little flame a torch
所以他们基本上创造了一个较小的火焰 一个火炬
which then is used to ignite the main combustion chambers.
然后用来点燃主燃烧室
So they're reusable.
所以它们是可以重复使用的
They can't get into a situation
这样就不会遇到这种情况
where they won't re-light the engine because they've run out of ignition propellant
一旦用完点火剂就不能重新点燃发动机
like what happened to the first falcon heavy core.
类似的情况发生在了第一枚重型猎鹰火箭的芯级上面
Now there's no official word on this from SpaceX.
现在SpaceX公司还没有官方的说法
But most people now believe the green is from copper in the engine which is basically being destroyed.
但现在大多数人认为绿色是来自损坏的发动机中的铜
This green is a sign of what we call engine rich exhaust.
这种绿色标志着一种废气的排出 这被我们称为富发动机燃烧 的废气
That is not something you want to have happen.
这不会是你想要发生的事情
It means the engine is destroying itself from the inside.
这意味着发动机正在从内部破坏自己
Now Elon has since told us that they observed low pressure in the fuel header tank
现在马一龙又告诉我们 他们发现头部储罐的压力很低
and that explains everything.
这就解释了一切
If you get low fuel pressure suddenly you can't run one of the engines it flames out
如果你的燃料压力突然变低 其中一台发动机就会无法运行 从而熄火
but moreover the other one that continues burning it's now getting way more oxygen than it should
但另外一台还在继续燃烧 它现在得到的氧气会比它应得的多得多
and instead of blowing a nice clean mixture of oxygen and propellant through the engine,
那么这台发动机就不会吹出干净的氧气和推进剂的混合物
it's blowing an oxygen-rich mixture through the entire thing
而只会在整台发动机中吹出富氧混合物
and that is just attacking the metal,
而这只会攻击金属
burning it and that is the green flame we are seeing out.
并(氧化)燃烧它 这就是我们看到的绿色火焰
And of course the engine is destroying itself.
当然 发动机也在自我毁灭
It's not generating any thrust.
它没有产生任何推力
And that's why they just slammed into the ground going too fast
所以航天器才会以过快的速度撞向地面
and the whole vehicle crushed pancaked.
而整个航天器都摔碎摔扁了
The nose cone is left and it does look pretty impressive sitting there on the pad.
鼻锥被留下了 坐在着陆场上 看上去很震撼
But overall this has been an amazingly successful test.
但总的来说 这是一次非常成功的测试
They launched.
他们发射了
They showed their control over the ascent all the way to 12 000 meters.
他们展示了他们对上升段的控制 一直到12km
They demonstrated the transition to the belly flop. Control the belly flop.
他们展示了向机腹翻转的过渡 对机腹翻转的控制
They reignited those engines and transitioned back into a vertical and they were on target.
他们重新点燃了那些发动机 然后过渡到垂直状态 并且正对着目标
They were right over their landing pad.
他们在着陆台的正上方
So they have another prototype ready to go.
那么他们有另一个原型机准备好了
I presume before they fly it again,
我想会在他们下次飞行之前
they're going to look at the header tank pressurization system.
他们会研究头部储罐加压系统
They might even try some longer duration test fires with this header system.
甚至可能会使用这个头部储罐来尝试进行一些持续时间较长的测试点火
So the pressurization comes from autogenous pressurization.
那么(头部储罐的)加压来自于自生增压
That means that some of the propellant that goes into the engines is heated by the combustion
这意味着一些进入发动机的推进剂会通过燃烧室加热
and then they boil that off and send it back into the tanks to provide pressurization.
汽化 并将其作为加压气体送回储罐中
And maybe that loop is too long.
那么也许这个循环太长了
Obviously the engine's lit for long enough that they could demonstrate that transition.
很明显 足够长的发动机点火时间可以验证这个(机腹翻转)过渡的可行性
It's also possible something about the forces in that transition and the fuel flow
也有可能是在那个过渡过程中 受力和燃料流动的问题
meant that they weren't able to pressurize the tanks correctly.
这就意味着他们不能正确地给储罐加压
It's a very dynamic situation and it is a very new maneuver.
这是一个非常动态的情况 也是一个非常新的机动
I will probably find out more
我可能会发现更多的(问题)
and soon no doubt they will clear up this mess.
而很快 毫无疑问地 他们将清理这个烂摊子
And SN9 will be ready to fly.
而SN9将准备好进行飞行
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全